Robert A. Luke Papers
Robert A. Luke Papers
1925-1990
1955-1980
Luke, Robert A.
3.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American adult educator, includes primarily his writings (articles, papers, books, drafts, speeches) plus two scrapbooks
2464386
Biographical History
Robert Luke was an American educator specializing in adult education. He served as Chair of the Community Organization Committee of the American Association for Adult Education (AAAE) from 1947 to 1948 and as Associate Executive Secretary of the Department of Adult Education of the National Education Association (NEA) from 1949 to 1951. In 1950, he was a member of the joint committee that laid out the structure for what would become the Adult Education Association of the United States (AEA/USA). He was also a member of the Coalition of Adult Education Organizations and a member of the Planning Committee for the 1969 Galaxy Conference of Adult Education Organizations. From 1964 to 1975, Dr. Luke served as International Secretary of the Adult Education Committee of the World Confederation of Organizations of the Teaching Profession. He was member (1984-1986) and then Chair (1986-1988) of the AAACE Publications Standing Service Unit.
Dr. Luke authored a number of articles, monographs, books, handbooks, and pamphlets over his career, including several for teachers (and trainers of teachers) of deaf adults (published under the auspices of Gallaudet University in Washington, DC) and a number focusing on inservice teacher education. As executive secretary of the Adult Education Council of Metropolitan Cincinnati, he chaired the Committee on Community Organization of the American Association for Adult Education which produced the paper, "Community Education in Action" (1948). He was the author of The NEA and Adult Education: A Historical Review 1921-1972, a research project that compiled the history and accomplishments of the National Education Association and which contributed greatly to the heritage of adult and continuing education. His editorship of The Teaching Profession and the Worldwide Literacy Program impacted the scene of adult and continuing education beyond the boundaries of the United States.
Robert Luke received many awards for his outstanding contributions to the field of continuing education. In 1987, the AAACE awarded him its Outstanding Service Medallion and in 1988 he received the AAACE President's Award for his exceptional leadership in adult and continuing education. He was inducted into the International Adult and Continuing Education Hall of Fame in 2000.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Robert A. Luke Papers consists of the files and writings of the American adult educator and author, with some memorabilia and photographs.
Biographical material contains clippings about Dr. Luke and a number of photographs, most from the 1950s and 1960s. Subject files are for the most part as Luke had them arranged and include among other things historical information on the Adult Education Act, a large amount of material on teacher inservice education, an eyewitness account by Luke of the Los Angeles Teachers Strike in April 1970, reports from Luke on his experiences training adult educators in Thailand, and notes and correspondence concerning an oral history project on the history of adult education. Conference proceedings, arranged chronologically, contains programs from the conferences of various adult education organizations ranging from the 1925 National Education Association Convention to the 39th Annual Adult Education Conference in 1990. Projects comprises material relating to projects that Dr Luke was involved in as director, consultant, board member, or in some other non-author capacity including Project Alphabet, a highly successful televised literacy course, and "The Story of Wiston," a filmstrip presentation based on one of Luke's case studies.
By far the majority of the material comprises Dr. Luke's Writings. This includes articles, books, speeches, reports, newsletters, workshop outlines and scripts for a videotaped series. Of particular interest are the draft and final copies of his extensive history of the National Education Association, The NEA and Adult Education: A Historical Review 1921-1972; material from Coahoma Junior College's Professor Emeritus Project and the NEA's Teacher Inservice Education Project; and copies of two of Luke's handbooks for teachers of deaf adults, published by Gallaudet University.
Memorabilia comprises two scrapbooks, one commemorating Luke's ten-year anniversary with NAPSAE and the other commerating his retirement. Miscellaneous includes two audiocassettes (a radio broadcast in company with George Aker and Paul Sheats, two other notable adult educators, and an interview with educator Leonard Oliver); several books by other authors on the Adult Education Act; a dissertation covering adult education in America from 1930-1939; and a variety of printed material.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Luke, Robert A.; Adult Education Association; American Association for Adult and Continuing Education; National Association for Public School Adult Education; Adult education, United States; Evening and continuation schools, United States; Teachers' workshops; Teachers of the deaf; Teachers, Training of, Research; Teachers, Training of, Thailand; Teachers, Training of, United States; Articles; Speeches; Drafts; Proceedings; Dissertations; Educators
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert A. Luke
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Clippings about, 1951; 1976 (Box 1)
  - Notes (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Adult Education Act, history and evolution of the Adult Education Act, including remarks before the Senate Subcommittee (Box 1)
  - ERIC, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Holden, John B. (Box 1)
  - In-service education
    - Articles (Box 1)
    - Conference and workshop outlines (Box 1)
    - Needs assessment (Box 1)
    - NEA views (Box 1)
    - Negotiations strategies (Box 1)
    - Printed material (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Los Angeles teachers' strike, Apr 1970; eyewitness account by Luke (Box 1)
  - NEA Teacher Center Network (Box 1)
  - Okes, Imogen, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Oral history project, 1984-1986; 1988 (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Association for Adult Continuing Education (PAACE), 1981 (Box 1)
  - Stephson, R.O.G., 1970 (Box 1)
  - Stubblefield, Harold, 1987; 1988,; 1990; includes writings by Stubblefield (Box 1)
  - Thailand reports, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Conference proceedings
  - National Education Association Convention, 1925 (Box 2)
  - International Adult Education Conference Proceedings, 1959 (Box 2)
  - UNESCO Regional Seminar, 1964 (Box 2)
  - 39th Annual Adult Education Conference, 1990 (Box 2)
- Projects
  - Operation Alphabet (director), ca. 1966 (Box 2)
  - Project Interchange (director), ca. 1967 (Box 2)
  - The Story of Wiston: Association Participation in Inservice Education (wrote case study), 1979 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Published, 1952-1981; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Drafts, 2 folders (Box 2, 3)
  - Books
    - A Guide to Participation in international conferences and study seminars, draft copy, includes review; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - How to Train Teachers to Train Adults, 1971 (Box 3)
    - The NEA and Adult Education: A Historical Review 1921-1972, draft and 2 final copies; 5 folders (Box 3, 4)
    - The Planning, Implementation, Financing and Management of Continuing Education Programs for Deaf Adults, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Strategies and Models for Developing Adult Career Education, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Teacher-Centered In-Service Education: Planning and Products, 1980 (Box 4)
    - Welcome to the Quiet Life: An Orientation Manual for Teachers (and Trainers of Teachers) of Deaf Adults, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Speeches (Box 4)
  - Reports
    - Inservice Education Project, National Education Association, 1979; 4 folders (Box 4, 5)
    - Professor Emeritus Project, Coahoma Junior College, 1980; 1981; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellany
    - "Adult Education" (Vocational and Professional Monographs No. 29), 1955 (Box 5)
    - Guides to the Discussion of Problems of Inflation (discussion guide), ca 1971? (Box 5)
    - "How to Make Church Committees More Effective" (workshop outline), 1956 (Box 5)
    - "Teaching Tips for Graduate School Faculty" (video script/narration) (Box 5)
    - "Teacher/Learning Effectiveness" (information sheet), 1976 (Box 5)
    - "Techniques for Teachers of Adults" (newsletter) Vol. IX no. 2, Nov 1968 (Box 5)
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Scrapbooks
    - [Untitled], 1962; commemoration of ten years of service (Oversize 1)
    - "BOB LUKE in deep appreciation", 1969; commemoration of retirement (Oversize 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Audiocassettes
    - Adult education radio broadcast, includes George Aker, Paul Sheats, Robert Luke (Oversize 2)
    - Len Oliver interview, 21 Apr 1985 (Oversize 2)
  - Books (by others)
    - Bradford, Leland P. National Training Laboratories - Its History: 1947-1970 (Oversize 1)
    - Leahy, Meredyth A. The Adult Education Act: A Guide to the Literature and Funded Projects, 1991 (Oversize 1)
    - Rose, Amy. Ends or Means: An Overview of the History of the Adult Education Act, 1991 (Oversize 1)
  - Dissertation, "The Short Happy Life of a Learning Society: Adult Education in America 1930-1939" by Ronald J. Hilton (Box 5)
  - Printed material, 2 folders (Box 5)